[Bret] What do you do
when your friends think
you’re the boy who cried wolf?
Matt Kellner had gone missing
in the dead of night sometime
in September of 1981.
[breathing shakily]
[Bret] But oddly, no one
in my social circle
was that concerned about it.
Looking back, I realize that’s
the gift of youth.
You think you’ll live forever.
I bet Matt moved to Big Sur
to deal drugs,
get out of the LA rat race.
[Robert] I agree.
I mean, who wouldn’t?
I hear
the Esalen Institute’s amazing.
What?
That’s lunacy. What about
the blood-stained backpack
they found?
[sighs] Hon, I love you,
but why are you so drawn
to worst-case scenarios?
You didn’t even know him.
Don’t mourn a death that
hasn’t officially happened.
- Can we talk
about happier things?
- Please. I need a cig.
[Susan chuckles]
[Bret] But then came
October 1st, the so-called
first day of spooky season.
October 1st was officially
The Day the Fun Died.
Because that’s the day
The Trawler got Really Rhonda.
[♪ dark synth music plays]
[all laughing]
[Bret] Really Rhonda was in
our class,
and everyone loved her.
Everyone thought
she was hilarious.
Her father was a big ICM agent
who represented
Sally Kellerman.
He paid the school
a handsome fee every year
to assure that Rhonda
would be assimilated
and not locked away
in the dungeon
that was a special needs class.
If X and B are both
positive real numbers...
[Bret] Today
we would understand
that Rhonda suffered
from a neurological condition,
but back then we just thought
she was darkly
and convulsively...
- [giggles]
- ...impulsive.
- [students laugh]
- Rhonda, please stop it.
I wanna fuck Chewbacca, motherfucker.
- [Bret] And a real
truth teller.
- [students laugh]
- [Flanigan] Rhonda,
do you want detention?
- Um...
George Washington sucks cocks
in hell, motherfucker!
Suck it, lick it,
fucking ass-face! Fuck.
- [students laugh]
- Really, Rhonda? Really?
[Bret] And from that moment on,
that’s what we all called her.
Really Rhonda.
[♪ ambient music playing]
I always felt an affection
for Rhonda.
Because during one
of her outbursts,
she could have easily
told the truth
about me,
called me a fag or a gayface,
but she was kind to me.
I felt she purposely edited out
my secret truth.
Protected me somehow from
the pubescent cruelty
of the other kids.
My favorite thing about Rhonda
was that she would not
get off the disco roller trend
long after it was over.
She just didn’t care
what people thought about her.
Can you imagine
the gift of that?
Really Rhonda is such
a good skater.
She’s even better than Cher.
[Bret] Disco roller skating
is important to this tale,
because that’s
what she was doing
when she was taken.
[♪ "Don’t Stand
So Close to Me" plays]
There was only one disco roller
derby place left
in town in 1981.
And Rhonda was the only patron
at Wheels that night
of October 1st.
The Trawler knew that,
the loneliness of the place.
And on that night, he snatched
Really Rhonda
from her happy place.
♪♪ Young teacher ♪
And out of all of our lives.
♪♪ The subject of
Schoolgirl fantasy ♪
♪♪ She wants him so badly ♪
♪♪ Knows what she wants to be ♪
♪♪ Inside her, there’s longing ♪
♪♪ This girl’s an open page ♪
♪♪ Bookmarking,
She’s so close now ♪
♪♪ This girl is half his age ♪
♪♪ Don’t stand, don’t stand so ♪
♪♪ Don’t stand so close to me ♪
♪♪ Her friends are so jealous ♪
♪♪ You know how bad girls get ♪
♪♪ Sometimes it’s not so easy ♪
♪♪ To be the teacher’s pet ♪
♪♪ Temptation... ♪
[Bret] When Rhonda
missed her curfew...
♪♪ So bad it makes him cry ♪
...her parents reported
her missing.
[siren blares]
[police chattering]
[Bret] The police immediately
checked out
the scene at Wheels.
- I’ll check around back.
- Got it.
[Bret] And that’s when
they found bloodstains.
[officer] Over here.
[Bret] Telltale clues
of a violent struggle.
I went to the scene
of the crime the next day,
oddly, instinctively.
The place Rhonda
had joyously twirled
the night before was deserted.
The rotating disco ball,
once a symbol of joy,
seemed sad to me, mournful.
Slowly twirling like
a flag at half-mast
to announce
all the ends of things
that 1981 had taken from us.
Matt.
Roller disco.
Really Rhonda.
And our sense of security.
[♪ sinister music plays]
[Rhonda whimpering]
Please, please.
Please, please, help me.
[whimpers]
[breathing shakily]
[gasps]
[whimpering]
[The Trawler] Eat it.
[screaming]
[Bret] It took about three days
for everything
to go back to normal,
and for everyone
to forget about Matt
and Rhonda.
[no audible dialogue]
[Debbie] Oh, my God.
I love it when we skip lunch
on the quad
and kick it at the Hamlet.
[Debbie] Yeah, me too.
Anyone want half my lunch?
- [Robert] Ooh.
- [chuckles] Oh.
Okay. [giggles]
Okay, listen up.
Don’t forget
to take your Flintstones
vitamins this month--
Or your diet pills.
Saturday is Robert’s,
and next Thursday is Dance Off!
and no one is allowed
to be hungover
because on Sunday,
we all need to practice.
Seriously?
That Dance Off!
thing is really happening?
Oh, my God.
I thought you were joking.
Does it look
like I’m joking, Bret?
- [♪ "Rapture" plays]
- [dancers cheering]
[Bret] Dance Off! was
a daily televised
cable access show
that featured regular
teenagers dancing
to the hot hits of the day.
Teenagers like us.
A Los Angeles institution,
it had its heyday in 1974
and refused to die.
♪♪ Toe to toe
Dancing very close ♪
[Bret] Debbie had been obsessed
with the idea
ever since Corazon Cha Cha
Rodriguez had gone on
and held the camera’s attention
for the length
of an entire Blondie song.
And not just any Blondie song.
"Rapture," six minutes
and 31 seconds.
Debbie saw that hot lava fame
and she wanted it for herself.
Becoming a star was
her secret ambition, but she
was too cool to ever admit it.
♪♪ Stepping lightly ♪
♪♪ Hang each night in rapture ♪
I gotta say, I hate that show.
Okay, well, it’s a rite
of passage classic in
this town, and it’s happening.
Guys, don’t you
think it’s kind of
a bad look to be partying on TV
- with classmates missing?
- [sighing] Okay.
Well, it’s what I want. It’s
done, and you’re all coming.
You’re welcome. [sighs]
Okay, so that’s it then?
We just don’t care anymore
about Rhonda or Matt?
Look, Bret, I’m not trying
to speak for the group here,
but I’m gonna speak
for the group.
- Rhonda and Matt
what’s-his-face--
- [Susan, Bret] Kellner.
They’re missing. They haven’t
been declared dead.
Maybe they ran away.
Oh, Bret, before I forget,
do you want to go shopping
with me after school
for homecoming?
- Tuxedo Warehouse?
- [Robert] Tuxedo Warehouse?
- Is it too, uh...
- [Robert] You guys have
that on the coast?
...I don’t know, GQ?
I think maybe not GQ enough.
[Susan groans]
Homecoming.
I don’t even want to go.
What do you mean you
don’t wanna go? W-Why do you
keep saying that repeatedly?
You have to go.
You and Thom
are totally gonna win
homecoming king and queen.
Aren’t we a little old
for homecoming?
[Robert] I would agree
with that.
Homecoming feels like a word
that’s, you know,
partial to overweight
Midwesterners
who make floats out of
toilet paper scraps
and suffer from gout.
[Debbie, Susan chuckle]
It’s not like I even have
an outfit.
You know what you would
look great in?
A simple black slip dress,
something fresh, modern.
- [Susan] Hmm.
- [Robert] No jewelry.
Just décolletage.
Décolletage?
Maybe we should cancel
the party too, you know.
It’s Robert’s
big welcome party, Bret.
It’s my big
welcome party, Bret.
It’s gonna be like
Capote’s Black and White Ball.
I’m so excited, thrilled.
Et cetera.
Bret’s right.
We should do something.
Maybe we should post flyers.
That’s a great idea.
Do something proactive.
Why don’t me and you
do it together, Susan?
[♪ distorted eerie music plays]
Waitress,
some more fries, please.
We’re asking anyone
with information about Rhonda
to please come forward.
You won’t be in trouble.
The only way we’re gonna
find these kids
is if we look.
Or if they show up.
Right.
All of us have been haunted
by the story of Etan Patz,
six-year-old boy
who disappeared outside
his home in SoHo, New York.
Was he kidnapped?
Was he murdered?
We don’t know.
What we do know
is that because his picture
appeared on every milk
carton in America,
his face is burned into
the minds of the people who
are going to bring him home.
That is why we are
handing out bottles
of Really Rhonda water
to increase awareness--
- And hydration.
- [chuckles softly]
If you can’t find a Perrier,
reach for a Really Rhonda
bottled water.
Thanks again to Rhonda’s dad
and all the heroes at ICM
for sponsoring our flyer,
hydration,
and the Rescue Rhonda Fund.
Bravo, ICM.
Now, AV club, hit it.
[♪ "Help Me, Rhonda" playing]
Zero mention of Matt.
- Unbelievable.
- I’m sure they’ll get to him.
I think the line
of awareness products for Matt
Kellner could be historic.
I think the line
of awareness products for Matt
Kellner could be historic.
"Bring Matt Home" pencils.
"Where Is Matt?"
terry cloth come rags.
It’s not funny, Thom.
I know,
but my dad used to tell me
to look on the sunny side,
and that’s what I’m trying
to do for you.
♪♪ It wouldn’t take much time ♪
♪♪ For you to help me, Rhonda ♪
♪ Help me get her
Out of my heart ♪
[sniffs] What are you wearing?
Kouros.
[giggles] It smells so sexy.
Thanks.
It’s for men.
[chuckles] Yeah,
you can really tell.
- [Susan] Hi. For Rhonda.
Rescue Rhonda.
- [Robert] Help Rhonda.
- Let’s bring her home.
- [Debbie] If she wanted to,
she could be such a slut.
There’s nothing stopping her.
I’ve always admired that.
You’re a really good friend.
I am.
♪♪ She was gonna be my wife
And I was gonna be her man ♪
♪♪ But she let another guy
Come between us ♪
♪♪ And it ruined our plan ♪
It’s sparkling, like Rhonda.
You are really gunning
for homecoming.
That’s not what this is.
God, Thom, it’s the ’80s.
Don’t be so cynical.
[Susan, Thom giggling]
♪♪ Help me, Rhonda
Help, help me, Rhonda ♪
[♪ piano playing]
[sniffs]
So tell me what your script
is about.
Oh, I dropped the treatment off
with Steven. Did he not--
Oh, yeah, I received it.
I read it.
Steven loves it, by the way.
[smacks lips]
I just don’t know
what it’s about.
I-I mean, why this story?
Why now?
Well, the character is me.
A version of me anyway.
- His name is Bret Ellis.
- Hmm.
Well, that makes it
interesting to you.
That doesn’t make
it interesting to others.
Listen, every great movie
ever made is about loss.
The loss of love, friendship,
innocence, ideals,
personal injury lawsuit.
So what has Bret Ellis lost?
Like, um...
my virginity?
Speak on that.
[car engine revs]
Where are we going?
Secret street. Connects
Beverly Hills to the Valley.
I thought that was just
an urban legend.
No, not an urban legend,
a suburban fact.
And only three people that I
know of have the combination
to the gates.
- Beatty.
- [engine revs]
Nicholson.
And me.
[tires squeal]
[engine rumbles]
[♪ intriguing synth
music plays]
[exhales]
8-1-7-0-6-6-6.
[♪ music continues]
[♪ music fades, ends]
[engine stops]
[breathes deeply]
Sometimes I come up here
to be alone.
You could too, you know.
Think about your script.
To get inspiration
as an artist.
This view is so inspirational.
We could, uh...
We could come
be alone together.
[engine rumbling]
I thought you said
only three people have
the code to this road.
I said that I know of.
Could just be Jack’s gardener
or picture hanger.
Who knows?
[hand brake creaks]
Terry?
Yeah?
Could you...
take me home?
Homework.
[♪ ambient music playing]
Yeah.
[engine starts]
[Bret] After Terry
dropped me off,
I knew automatically
that I would be heading
to Matt Kellner’s house.
When I turned
onto Haskell Avenue,
I was suddenly struck
with a fear
I had never experienced before.
I was suddenly struck
with a fear
I had never experienced before.
It was an adrenaline that acted
as a warning for me
to save myself,
but also mixed
with an overwhelming
compulsion to move forward...
no matter how I felt,
how afraid I was.
[♪ racy synth music playing]
[♪ suspenseful music plays]
This was the last place
I had seen Matt.
I missed him.
I wanted him back.
I was on a mission
to find clues
about his disappearance.
I found them.
[♪ music continues]
[sighs]
As I sat there
in the soft moonlight,
I realized that, at 18,
I was already staring
into my past.
I remember this being
one of my first moments
when I realized how
powerful memory was.
Or at least it was
the first time
it hurt the most.
[sniffles]
[crying]
[exhales]
[phone ringing]
- Hello.
- [static on phone]
[caller breathing heavily]
Where’s Matt?
What have you done with him?
Where’s Rhonda?
- Why are you doing this?
- [heavy breathing continues]
Robert.
Robert!
[dial tone]
[♪ ominous music plays]
[inhales sharply]
[sighs]
[exhaling, sniffling]
[crowd applauding, cheering]
Wow.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
Most people who win this award
thank everybody
that helped them
get to this moment.
Instead, I’d like to take
this brief time I have here
in the white-hot spotlight...
to say what I really feel
about how I got here.
How I clawed my way up
that mountain of success
- alone.
- [applause resumes]
To my first modeling agent
who told me
I had an ass like a pear
and would probably be
a Sears catalog model
at best...
- fuck you, bitch.
- [crowd cheers]
Look at me now. [sniffles]
To my daughter
who’s watching tonight...
you are the disappointment
of my life.
And to my husband...
To my husband...
who regularly reminds me that
I am a worthless
piece of shit...
[slow clapping]
Lizzie.
Are you still holding on to
that actress thing?
How deeply sad.
You go ahead
and make fun of me, Terry.
I’m fucking used to it,
you know.
But I know I could have been
more than this,
more than just your stupid wife
rattling around this mausoleum
like a fucking ghost.
Sue told me I have
an "it" factor.
Sue Mengers told you that
at a dinner party
where she was stoned
out of her mind.
Everybody feels sorry
for you, Liz,
so they fill your addled mind
with positive reinforcement
that you don’t deserve.
Haven’t all the therapists
I paid for
helped you understand that?
If you would have let me,
I could have pursued my dream
and been somebody,
instead of your
fucking plus-one.
Sure, absolutely.
Keep practicing
your speech, babe,
with one of my three Oscars.
But don’t forget to thank
your coke dealer.
[♪ seething synth music plays]
- [exhales shakily]
- [♪ music ends]
[Bret] I already knew
Robert Mallory was a liar.
He was the only one at lunch
who didn’t show
a flicker of concern
about the missing kids.
Almost like he knew
they were already gone.
[♪ "Games Without
Frontiers" playing]
♪♪ Hans plays with Lotte
Lotte plays with Jane ♪
[Bret] I committed myself
to the pursuit
of a single goal:
track Robert and prove
he was The Trawler.
♪♪ Suki plays with Leo ♪
♪♪ Sacha plays with Britt ♪
♪♪ Adolf builds a bonfire
Enrico plays with it ♪
[whistling]
♪♪ Whistling tunes we hide
In the dunes by the seaside ♪
[whistling]
♪♪ Whistling tunes we’re kissing
Baboons in the jungle ♪
♪♪ It’s a knockout ♪
♪♪ If looks could kill
They probably will ♪
♪♪ In games
Without frontiers... ♪
[Bret] Cielo Drive.
This is where,
almost exactly 12 years ago,
three members
of the Manson Family
stabbed and killed
Jay Sebring, Abigail Folger,
Wojciech Frykowski,
Steven Parent,
and nine-months-pregnant
Sharon Tate.
I was obsessed
with Joan Didion’s
account of the Manson murders.
I read it over and over again.
I retyped the sentences
on my typewriter, trying to
understand their architecture.
Like all aspiring writers
of my generation,
I wanted to write like Didion.
With restraint,
economy,
and total control.
If I could write like that...
I could be like that.
Or so I thought.
♪♪ It’s a knockout ♪
♪♪ If looks could kill
They probably will ♪
♪♪ In games without frontiers
War without tears ♪
[♪ song ends]
[Bret] I didn’t know
what he was doing there.
I only knew
what I was doing there:
"Telling myself
a story in order to live."
Part of me just wanted to knock
on the door or force my way in.
What if Matt was
in there right now?
Or Really Rhonda?
Who knew what sort of
hideous agony
he was inflicting?
Were they lying
there bloody and beaten,
mangled and mutilated,
screaming out
for someone, anyone,
to come to the rescue?
[exhales]
Being afraid is so lame,
I kept telling myself.
Being afraid is so lame
and you’re not a pussy.
Eventually I would find out
that this remote
mysterious house
was a rental property
of Robert Mallory’s aunt.
Later, when the police
interviewed me,
I told them the truth about
what I suspected
was in the bag.
A human head.
[♪ dark synth music plays]
- [car door closes]
- [engine starts, revving]
[lock rattles]
[♪ music intensifies]
[♪ "Edge of Seventeen" plays]
Hello.
♪♪ Just like
The white-winged dove ♪
♪♪ Sings a song
It sounds like she’s singin’ ♪
♪♪ Ooh, ooh, ooh ♪
♪♪ Just like
The white-winged dove
♪ Sings a song... ♪
Hello?
♪♪ Ooh, baby, ooh, said, "Ooh" ♪
- ♪♪ He was no more ♪
♪♪ Than a baby then ♪
♪♪ Well, he seemed
Brokenhearted ♪
♪♪ Somethin’ within him ♪
♪♪ But the moment
That I first laid ♪
♪♪ Eyes on him ♪
♪♪ All alone
On the edge of seventeen ♪
[Bret] Being afraid is so lame.
♪♪ Just like
The white-winged dove ♪
♪♪ Sings a song
It sounds like she’s singin’ ♪
♪♪ Ooh, baby, ooh, said, "Ooh" ♪
♪♪ Just like
The white-winged dove ♪
[Bret] Don’t be lame.
♪♪ It sounds
Like she’s singin’ ♪
♪♪ Said, "Ooh, baby,
Ooh," said, "Ooh" ♪
♪♪ Well, I went today ♪
[clatters]
♪♪ Maybe I will go
Again tomorrow ♪
♪♪ Yeah, yeah ♪
Hello?
♪♪ Well, the music there ♪
♪ Well, it was
hauntingly familiar ♪
♪♪ When I see you doin’
What I try to do for me ♪
♪♪ With the words of a poet ♪
♪♪ And a voice from a choir ♪
♪♪ And a melody ♪
♪♪ And nothin’ else mattered ♪
♪♪ Just like
The white-winged dove ♪
♪♪ Sings a song
It sounds like she’s singin’ ♪
♪♪ Ooh, baby, ooh, said, "Ooh" ♪
♪♪ Just like
The white-winged dove ♪
♪♪ Sings a song
It sounds like she’s singin’ ♪
♪♪ Said, "Ooh, baby,
Ooh," said, "Ooh" ♪
[metal clanks]
♪♪ Just like
The white-winged dove ♪
♪♪ Sings a song
It sounds like she’s singin’ ♪
♪♪ Ooh, baby, ooh, said, "Ooh" ♪
♪♪ Just like
The white-winged dove ♪
♪♪ Sings a song
It sounds like she’s singin’ ♪
[muffled groaning]
♪♪ Ooh, baby, ooh, said, "Ooh" ♪
♪♪ Well, then suddenly ♪
♪♪ There was no one left
Standin’ in the hall ♪
[muffled groaning]
♪♪ Yeah, yeah,
In a flood of tears ♪
♪♪ That no one really
Ever heard fall at all... ♪
[muffled groaning continues]
♪♪ Up the stairs
And down the hall ♪
♪ And not to find an answer ♪
♪♪ Just to hear the call
Of a night bird ♪
[muffled groaning continues]
- ♪♪ Singin’, "Come away" ♪
- ♪♪ Come away ♪
Please, please, please,
just please let me go home.
Please let me go home.
Motherfucker, cock,
shit, cunt licker.
Fuck. Oh, I’m sorry.
No, I’m sorry.
Fuck. [groans]
Please, please,
please. [whimpers]
[whimpers] No, no, no!
[screaming]
Get the fuck off of me!
♪♪ Well, I hear you
In the morning ♪
♪♪ And I hear you ♪
♪♪ My love ♪
[muffled groaning continues]
♪♪ I’m a few years
Older than you... ♪
[groans]
♪♪ Just like
The white-winged dove ♪
♪♪ Sings a song
It sounds like she’s singin’ ♪
[♪ song fades out]
[♪ eerie music plays]
[rumbling]
♪♪ Just like
The white-winged dove ♪
♪♪ Sings a song
It sounds like she’s singin’ ♪
♪♪ Ooh, ooh, ooh ♪
♪♪ Just like
The white-winged dove ♪
♪♪ Sings a song
It sounds like she’s singin’ ♪
♪♪ Ooh, baby, ooh, said, "Ooh" ♪
♪♪ And the days go by
Like a strand in the wind ♪
♪♪ In the web that is my own
I begin again ♪
- ♪♪ Said to my friend, "Baby" ♪
- ♪♪ Everything stops ♪
♪♪ Nothin’ else mattered ♪
- ♪♪ He was no more ♪
♪♪ Than a baby then ♪
♪♪ Well,
He seemed brokenhearted ♪
♪♪ Somethin’ within him ♪
♪♪ But the moment
That I first laid ♪
♪♪ Eyes on him ♪
♪♪ All alone on the edge of ♪
♪♪ Seventeen ♪
♪♪ Just like
The white-winged dove ♪
♪♪ Sings a song
It sounds like she’s singin’ ♪
♪♪ Ooh, baby, ooh, said, "Ooh" ♪
♪♪ Just like
The white-winged dove ♪
♪♪ Sings a song
It sounds like she’s singin’ ♪
♪♪ Ooh, baby, ooh, said, "Ooh" ♪
♪♪ Well, I went today ♪
♪ Maybe I will go
Again tomorrow ♪
♪♪ When I see you doin’
What I try to do for me ♪
♪♪ With the words of a poet ♪
♪♪ And a voice from a choir ♪
♪♪ And a voice from a choir ♪ ♪♪ And a melody ♪
♪♪ And a melody ♪
♪♪ And nothin’ else mattered ♪
♪♪ Just like
The white-winged dove ♪
♪♪ Sings a song
It sounds like she’s singin’ ♪
♪♪ Ooh, baby, ooh ♪